Contact

sdegarmoenp@aol.com

www.linkedin.com/in/seandegarmo (LinkedIn)

Top Skills

Critical Care Nursing ACLS

Sean DeGarmo, PhD

Director, APRN Initiatives at American Nurses Credentialing Center Houston, Texas

Summary

Advanced Practice Provider (APP) with 20 years of experience as nurse practitioner, clinical nurse specialist, flight nurse, researcher and educator in academic and non-academic institutions. Strategic visionary with expertise in solution identification and problem solving to achieve operational and efficiency goals. Effective team builder among multidisciplinary Advanced Practice Providers by facilitating communication and bridging gaps among healthcare providers, information technology specialists and executive leadership.

Experience

American Nurses Credentialing Center Director, APRN Initiatives April 2020 - Present (3 months) Silver Spring, Maryland, United States

The University of Texas Health Science Center at Houston (UTHealth)
Graduate Nursing Instructor
May 2006 - Present (14 years 2 months)
School of Nursing

Participate in the ongoing development, implementation, evaluation, and enhancement of nursing academic programs. Participate in program and course revisions to reflect program outcomes, AACN essentials, state board of nursing minimum standards, current evidence and best practice. Collaborate with faculty and staff members both within the School of Nursing and throughout the University and community to develop inter-professional academic and clinical opportunities. Collaborate with clinical sites in arranging student clinical experiences. Collaborate with clinical coordinators, program directors to identify the types of clinical experiences and sites needed for optimal clinical education of students. Assess and evaluate graduate nursing students through high fidelity simulation and practical skills in a clinical setting.

Deloitte Consulting Specialist Master September 2018 - November 2019 (1 year 3 months) Houston, Texas

Memorial Hermann Health System
Director of Advanced Practice Providers
August 2014 - February 2017 (2 years 7 months)
Houston, Texas

EmCare
Emergency Nurse Practitioner
March 2008 - August 2014 (6 years 6 months)

Frontier Healthcare Group (Liberty-Dayton and Winnie Community Hospital
Emergency Nurse Practitioner
February 2007 - August 2009 (2 years 7 months)
Winnie, Texas and Liberty, Texas

Air Evac Lifeteam
Flight Nurse
September 2006 - June 2007 (10 months)

Provided safe, comprehensive care to adult, pediatric, maternal and neonatal patients that were critically ill and/or injured in pre-hospital setting and during intra-facility transports. Utilized and implemented broad understanding and application of specialized principles and techniques of flight nursing practice, emergency procedures and diagnostics. Experienced in treatment of traumatic injuries (car/boating accidents, shootings, stabbings, assaults, falls, drownings, amputations, work related injuries); MI's and CVA's; cardiopulmonary and respiratory arrest.

Specialized Knowledge – Utilized specialized principles related to treating patients at altitude, scene calls, paramedicine, ACLS, PALS, ABLS, and ATCN. Operated autonomously utilizing protocols from Medical Director. Performed advanced airway techniques, central lines, chest tubs, advanced pharmacology (rapid sequence induction or pharmacologic assisted induction) monitor: ICP, Swan Ganz catheters.

Coordination of Care with Interdisciplinary Teams – Coordinated patient care requirements with pilots, mechanics, flight paramedic, fire department staff, chemical plan disaster and HAZMAT teams.

Memorial Hermann Health System CNS and Education Resource Specialist 2005 - 2006 (1 year)

PHI

Flight Nurse July 2004 - August 2005 (1 year 2 months)

Provided safe, comprehensive care to adult, pediatric, maternal and neonatal patients that were critically ill and/or injured in pre-hospital setting and during intra-facility transports. Utilized and implemented broad understanding and application of specialized principles and techniques of flight nursing practice, emergency procedures and diagnostics. Experienced in treatment of traumatic injuries (car/boating accidents, shootings, stabbings, assaults, falls, drownings, amputations, work related injuries); MI's and CVA's; cardiopulmonary and respiratory arrest.

Specialized Knowledge – Utilized specialized principles related to treating patients at altitude, scene calls, paramedicine, ACLS, PALS, ABLS, and ATCN. Operated autonomously utilizing protocols from Medical Director. Performed advanced airway techniques, central lines, chest tubs, advanced pharmacology (rapid sequence induction or pharmacologic assisted induction) monitor: ICP, Swan Ganz catheters.

Coordination of Care with Interdisciplinary Teams – Coordinated patient care requirements with pilots, mechanics, flight paramedic, fire department staff, chemical plan disaster and HAZMAT teams.

Phi Air Medical Flight Nurse 2004 - 2005 (1 year)

Provided safe, comprehensive care to adult, pediatric, maternal and neonatal patients that were critically ill and/or injured in pre-hospital setting and during intra-facility transports. Utilized and implemented broad understanding and application of specialized principles and techniques of flight nursing practice, emergency procedures and diagnostics. Experienced in treatment of traumatic injuries (car/boating accidents, shootings, stabbings, assaults, falls, drownings, amputations, work related injuries); MI's and CVA's; cardiopulmonary and respiratory arrest.

Specialized Knowledge – Utilized specialized principles related to treating patients at altitude, scene calls, paramedicine, ACLS, PALS, ABLS, and ATCN. Operated autonomously utilizing protocols from Medical Director. Performed advanced airway techniques, central lines, chest tubs, advanced

pharmacology (rapid sequence induction or pharmacologic assisted induction) monitor: ICP, Swan Ganz catheters.

Coordination of Care with Interdisciplinary Teams – Coordinated patient care requirements with pilots, mechanics, flight paramedic, fire department staff, chemical plan disaster and HAZMAT teams.

AMN Healthcare

Traveling Nurse September 2001 - July 2003 (1 year 11 months)

Provided care for patients in a variety of settings, primarily Level I Trauma Centers through American Mobile Nursing (observed, learned and participated in a variety of techniques in treating patients from acute to critical levels of care within hospitals comprised of 400-1000 beds, 40-50 bed ERs 15 bed pediatric ER, units with multiple trauma bays, and ICUs). Specialized in ER, trauma and Critical Care. Provided resuscitation of adult and pediatric patients. Assessed, treated, advocated for and carried out physician orders in caring for patients with injuries or illness related to trauma, medical, neurological, cardiovascular or surgical conditions; attended trauma call, coded patients and assisted in invasive procedures.

Cedars-Sinai Medical Center ER Travel Nurse 2001 - 2002 (1 year)

Provided resuscitation of adult and pediatric patients. Assessed, treated, advocated for and carried out physician orders in caring for patients with injuries or illness related to trauma, medical, neurological, cardiovascular or surgical conditions; attended trauma call, coded patients and assisted in invasive procedures.

Banner Health ICU Float RN, TICU RN, ER/Trauma RN 1999 - 2001 (2 years)

Education

The University of Texas Health Science Center at Houston (UTHealth)

Doctor of Philosophy - PhD, Healthcare Economics and BioInformatics · (2011 - 2017)

The University of Texas Health Science Center at Houston (UTHealth)

MSN, Clinical Nurse Specialist/ENP · (2004 - 2006)

The University of Texas Health Science Center at Houston (UTHealth)

Emergency Nurse Practitioner/CNS in Emergency Care · (2004 - 2006)

University of the Incarnate Word BSN, Nursing · (1995 - 1999)

University of Arizona Nursing · (1991 - 1994)